<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Separation convicted of profanation, oppression, persecution, [brace] rebellion, self-destruction, and antichristianism being a further evidence of the mischief of separation, as asserted by the most learned and pious Dr. Edw. Stillingfleet, Dean of St. Pauls / by Lewes Sharpe, rector of Moreton-Hampstead in Devon.</title>
            <author>Sharpe, Lewes.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 102 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A59578</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3006A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R37382</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">16412921</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 16412921</idno>
            <idno type="VID">105387</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A59578)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 105387)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1158:27)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Separation convicted of profanation, oppression, persecution, [brace] rebellion, self-destruction, and antichristianism being a further evidence of the mischief of separation, as asserted by the most learned and pious Dr. Edw. Stillingfleet, Dean of St. Pauls / by Lewes Sharpe, rector of Moreton-Hampstead in Devon.</title>
                  <author>Sharpe, Lewes.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 38 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.C. and Freeman Collins, to be sold by the booksellers of London and Exeter ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Stillingfleet, Edward, 1635-1699. --  Unreasonableness of separation.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Joshua XXII, 19 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:105387:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:105387:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>SEPARATION Convicted OF
<list>
                  <item>Prophanation,</item>
                  <item>Oppreſſion,</item>
                  <item>Perſecution,</item>
                  <item>Rebellion,</item>
                  <item>Self deſtruction, AND</item>
                  <item>Antichriſtianiſm</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Being a FURTHER EVIDENCE OF The Miſchief of Separation, As aſſerted by the moſt Learned and Pious Dr. <hi>EDW. STILLINGFLEET,</hi> DEAN of St. <hi>PA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LS.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Lewes Sharpe,</hi> Rector of <hi>Moreton-Hampſtead</hi> in <hi>Devon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>J. C.</hi> and <hi>Freeman Collins;</hi> to be ſold by the Book<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellers of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Exeter.</hi> 1681.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:105387:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:105387:2"/>
            <head>TO The very Reverend, and Right Worſhipful, D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Edw. Stillingfleet DEAN of St. <hi>PA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LS.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Onconformity unto, and Separation from the Church of <hi>England,</hi> having brought forth bold and daring Advocates to offer to the world, and that with a repeated diligence, Pleas for their Juſtification; 'twas high time for ſome dutiful Son of ſo innocent and indulgent a Mother, to awake, arm, and march forth out of his Tent, for her De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence and Vindication: And how ſeaſonably and obligingly you appeared, who are deſervedly reputed the <hi>Anteſignanus</hi> of the preſent Age, for the Proteſtant Cauſe and Intereſt, I can with more thank-ful Reſentments acknowledge, than with due Elogies repreſent; for I can tell you, Sir, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the leaſt ſuſpition of flattery, That ſo good a Cauſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing managed by ſuch an expert Champion for the Truth, the Conforming Sons of the Church are greatly confident, that you will rather need Spectators to congratulate your victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
<pb facs="tcp:105387:3"/>Succeſſes, than any Seconds to help you with any Succours in your Conteſts. Indeed you have ſo judiciouſly and learnedly ſtated the Caſe of ſinful Separation, and ſo directly and plainly applied it to the Authors and Fomen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of it here in <hi>England,</hi> that you may with much truth, and no immodeſty, ſay, <hi>Veni, vidi, vici.</hi> But 'tis your In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>felicity, that you have to do with ſuch Adverſaries, who, like an angry and revengeful ſort of Animals, which will ſhew their Teeth when they cannot bite, and bawl when they durſt not fight, rather than they will quietly and ſilent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly yield to the conquering force of your Arguments, they will raiſe a great Noiſe, and write much againſt them too, though to no purpoſe: and though you have done enough to ſhame them out of a diſputing and wrangling humour, yet you finde they become impudent, and rail and upbraid, yea, turn meer Buffoons, quibble and ſcoff it out; and when nothing elſe will do, they will flie to their ſure and old Refuge, their Obſtinacy, which they know to be ſo ſtrong an Hold againſt the power of Arguments, that the power of Miracles cannot demoliſh it. 'Tis true, they do not, with the Romaniſts, in their Conteſts with you, challenge to themſelves an Infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility; but yet they carry it as if they could not be deceived, accounting a perfective Change no commendable Improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but a vicious Weakneſs: and therefore that your friendly and compaſſionate Condeſcentions to inſtruct and convince them, have ſo highly diſpleaſed and provoked them, is not at all to be wondered at; for they take it to be an attempt to expoſe them, becauſe you hereby repreſent them as a ſort of men who are not altogether of the wiſeſt,
<pb facs="tcp:105387:3"/>but ſuch as have aſſented to Propoſitions, and engaged themſelves in anſwerable Practices, without taking due e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence and conſideration. And for ſuch Pretenders to Knowledge as they are, who are, or would be, admired for Gods moſt ſecret ones, to take up Opinions and agreeable Practices, and to plead and ſuffer for them, and after they have made a ſtrong and daring Party for them too, then to recant and lay them down, is a Puniſhment too great to be endured; an Argument of ſuch weakneſs and vanity of Minde, and of ſuch levity and unreſolvedneſs of Will, they durſt not own, leſt their Reputations and dependant Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts then become as little, as they perſwade themſelves now they are great. Beſides, you have charged Schiſm on a Separation from the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and you cannot make them underſtand what the Church of <hi>England</hi> is: and I will warrant no body elſe ſhall, unleſs he propound a Propoſition concerning it, which will gratifie their Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and accommodate their Intereſts; which no wiſe, good, and honeſt man will ever do. The Titles given to ſome of their Pamphlets are very goodly and ſpecious: here you have, <hi>A Chriſtian Temper;</hi> there, <hi>The Peaceable De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne;</hi> here, <hi>A Peace-Offering;</hi> there, <hi>A Plea for Peace;</hi> here, <hi>A true way to Concord;</hi> there, <hi>A Diſcourſe of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelical Love, Church-Peace and Unity:</hi> but they all joyn Iſſue in Declamations againſt the miſchief of Impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and conclude in Pleas for Nonconformity, and Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations of themſelves from Schiſm; that is, they repreſent the Church of <hi>England</hi> as a Tyrannical Impoſer, a Society of men uſurping and exerciſing Church-power for Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
<pb facs="tcp:105387:4"/>and not for Edification; unto whom no body ought to ſubmit and obey, but every body muſt oppoſe and defie. So that we muſt undo our ſelves, and betake us to a Stool of Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, before we can be in a meet capacity for a Chriſtian communion with them in Love, Peace, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity. And to give them their due, they are no Changelings in their common deſigne; they are all hard at it to pull down the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and to get themſelves uppermoſt; and if they happen to rid themſelves of Impoſitions, I can get a Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to aſſure you in their Names, that they are more peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble than to ſtomach it, and bring themſelves under them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain. Let there be no Laws made, and they will be very careful not to break them; Let it be lawful for every man to do that which is right in his own eyes, and they will be a very innocent ſort of people, and never offend. This, Sir, you know, is the true conſtruction of what they call the Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief of Impoſitions. Now although we know them ſo well, that we need not the help of a <hi>Melius Inquirendum</hi> to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver that they are one of the moſt unteachable as well as moſt ungovernable ſort of people in the world, againſt whom Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity is no longer ſafe than 'tis too ſtrong for them; yet I hope God hath mercy in ſtore for them, becauſe he hath ſo ſignally called you forth (who ſo very well underſtand their Diſeaſe and Remedy) for their Cure. And that the Work may proſper in your hands, and be throughly effected, to Gods Glory, this Church's Peace, and your own Satisfaction and Comfort, is the hearty and fervent Prayer of him that is,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Reverend Sir,</salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your moſt humble Servant,</hi> Lewes Sharpe.</signed>
               <dateline>Moreton-Hampſtead, <date>
                     <hi>Octob. 22. 1680.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:105387:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>JOSH. 22.19.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>Notwithſtanding, if the land of your poſſeſſion be unclean, then paſs ye over unto the land of the poſſeſſion of the Lord, wherein the Lords Tabernacle dwelleth, and take poſſeſſion among us: but rebel not againſt the Lord, nor rebel againſt us, in building you an Altar beſide the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar of the Lord our God.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE word <hi>[Notwithſtanding]</hi> is diſcretive, and plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly refers us to the Context for the right underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the words read to you. <hi>Iſrael</hi> having compleated the Conqueſt of their Enemies, and being in a peaceable poſſeſſion of the Promiſed Land, <hi>chap.</hi> 21.43, 44, 45. <hi>Joſhua,</hi> their Captain-General, calls an Aſſembly of the <hi>Reubenites, Gadites,</hi> and half Tribe of <hi>Manaſſeh,</hi> and having commended them for their Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to God and to himſelf, and for their Love and Fidelity to their Brethren, he commands them to get to their Tents, and to return to the Land of their poſſeſſion, which <hi>Moſes</hi> gave them on the other ſide of <hi>Jordan,</hi> v. 1, 2, 3, 4. And becauſe 'tis not enough to begin well, and for a ſeaſon to hold on in a good courſe; therefore as at their firſt Aſſembling he commended them for what they had alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy well done, ſo at their diſmiſſion he charged them to perſevere in well-doing: And ſo bleſſeth, and withal orders them, when they are returned home to their Brethren, that they make them Sharers with them in the Spoils of their Enemies, <hi>v.</hi> 5, 8. that it might ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear that the common good was a greater Incentive to their cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rageous Encounters, than a private gain; and that a preſent taſte and experience of the beneficial fruits of their Victory, might moſt effectually provoke their Brethren to joyn with them in Praiſes and Thankſgivings for it.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:105387:5"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 2. Now the <hi>Reubenites, Gadites,</hi> and half Tribe of <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> in their return, being come unto the borders of <hi>Jordan,</hi> do not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bine to erect triumphant Monuments of their ſignal Victories over their Enemies, but how to ſecure their religious intereſts in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon with their friends, in the Worſhip and Priviledges of the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle. Though the Soil they poſſeſs be different from that of the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> yet the Inhabitants of the one, as well as of the other, ſhall acknowledge the Lord of the Soil to be the ſame. Though they do not poſſeſs the ſame Land, yet they will enjoy the ſame God. And though their Habitations be at a greater diſtance from the place and ſymbols of Gods ſpecial preſence than thoſe of their Brethren, yet they will make a ſolemn Proteſt, and record a ſenſible Evidence for them, that they are as neerly related unto God, and have as good a claim to all the Rites and Memorials of his gracious Name and Commerce, as they.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 3. For this purpoſe they built an Altar over againſt the Land of <hi>Canaan</hi> in the borders of <hi>Jordan,</hi> v. 10, 11. not like that in the Tabernacle, for Sacrifices, but for a Memorial to ſucceeding Generations, that they and their Seed may reſort with the reſt of the Tribes to the Tabernacle, and partake with them in all the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices and priviledges of it, <hi>v.</hi> 10. comp. with 24. a practical demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, how highly they prized a Right to the fellowſhip of their Brethren in the ſame Rites of Religion, which they endeavour to entail to their Poſterities, as well as ſecure to themſelves.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 4. And what is the effect of this zeal for their God, and affection for their Brethren? Truely, it was here, as too often in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther caſes, that which was well meant was ill taken; for as ſoon as the other Tribes heard of this Altar, they were ſo alarm'd, that they preſently call a Council of War, ſuppoſing thoſe who were very lately their Champions to be their Enemies, are ſo enrag'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, that notwithſtanding their late uſefulneſs to them, and neer Relation with them, they ſeem to deſigne them as a Sacrifice for their Altar, <hi>v.</hi> 12. but before they will go to extremities with them, expoſe them to their revenge who expoſed themſelves for their defence, they will expoſtulate with them before they will do execution upon them: and therefore ſent choſen Meſſengers to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:105387:5"/>them to reaſon the caſe with them, <hi>v.</hi> 13. And 'tis well they did ſo; for though it was bad enough to judge before they tryed them, yet 'twould have been much worſe to perſecute and deſtroy them too.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 5. That they ſent Meſſengers to them, was an Argument that they were not implacable and inexorable: but the grievous offences they were commiſſioned to lay to their charge, was too ſtrong an Evidence, that there was in their Enterprize too much of a paſſionate Fury, and too little of a well-adviſed Charity: for, from meer jealouſie and ſuſpition, they attaint them with no lower crime than Rebellion againſt God and themſelves; that is, either an Apoſtacy to the Worſhip of a falſe God, or a Separation from the Worſhippers of the true. They thought the erection of a new Altar implied the adoration of a new God; and the conſecration of a new Tabernacle or Temple, a ſeparate religious Commerce and Communion from that formerly they had been obliged unto and exerciſed in; a guilt ſo tremendous, that it threatned deſtruction from God to them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 6. Now though this Charge be ſo very deep and heavy, that it looks rather like an invidious Accuſation, Challenge, and Defiance, than a charitable Embaſſage for Amity, Peace, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, and ſeems deſigned rather to Exaſperation than Accommoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; yet the words I have read to you, plainly evince, that the Intent was charitable, pacifick, and healing. For the words are an Expoſtulation, or a Reaſoning with them, to work them to a conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of what they had done, and the conſequences of it; that they might reclaim them rather by the ſtrength of Reaſon, than ruine them by the force of Arms. In them we have three things conſiderable:
<list>
                  <item>1. A Suppoſition, <hi>If the Land of your inheritance be unclean.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. A Conceſſion, <hi>Then paſs ye over into the poſſeſſion of the inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance of the Lord, wherein the Lords Tabernacle dwelleth, and take poſſeſſion among us.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. A Limitation of this, <hi>But rebel not againſt the Lord, nor rebel againſt us, in building you an Altar beſide the Altar of the Lord our God.</hi> I ſhall diſcourſe of each in order.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:105387:6"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 7. Here is a Suppoſition, <hi>If the Land of your inheritance be unclean.</hi> They may ſuppoſe, but not grant it; for their inheritance was undoubtedly part of the promiſed and holy Land, as well as the Land of <hi>Canaan.</hi> And indeed the Suppoſition is not grounded on any miſperſwaſion the <hi>Reubenites, Gadites,</hi> and half Tribe of <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> had concerning the Land, but on their own raſh and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitable jealouſie and ſuſpition. 'Tis very likely, that becauſe the Land which the <hi>Reubenites,</hi> &amp;c. were to poſſeſs, had not the Tabernacle and Altar in it, the onely place unto which all the Tribes were to reſort for the exerciſe of the publick Miniſteries and Rites of Religion, and there was no place like it on the other ſide of <hi>Jordan,</hi> they inferr'd this concluſion, That the <hi>Reubenites,</hi> &amp;c. were prejudiced againſt their inheritance, becauſe without the viſible ſigns of Gods ſpecial preſence. From whence by the way, without any digreſſion, we may obſerve, <hi>That Gods Church and People then thought, That that Land was unclean (that is, excluded from Gods ſpecial favour and protection) which had no Places by publick conſent ſet apart and conſecrated for the exerciſe of religious Worſhip and Communion.</hi> For as the firſt-Fruits under the Law were to ſanctifie and procure a Bleſſing upon the whole Harveſt; ſo Places dedicated and peculiarly appropriated to the publick Worſhip and Service of God, are for a Bleſſing to the whole Country and Land where they are, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84.3.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 8. But that which I deſigne principally to commend to your conſideration from the Suppoſition, is this, <hi>That a People pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing the Lord to be their God, from a miſtake and miſperſwaſion of the nature of things, I mean from a conceit that things are unholy and unclean which are not ſo, may ſeparate themſelves from a publick reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Commerce and Communion, and from the holy things of God.</hi> This the whole Congregation of the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſuppoſed the caſe of the <hi>Reubenites,</hi> &amp;c. to be. And this is really the caſe of many now; they are more led by Opinion than Truth, more under the power of Imagination and affection, than Reaſon and Religion. What is it which buildeth their Church, chuſeth their Teacher, preſcribeth their Diſcipline, meaſureth their Devotion, formeth their Prayers, compoſeth their Geſtures, and ordereth all
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:105387:6"/>their ſignifications of Reverence to God, but their Conceits and Phantaſies? Although it be not in the power of any mans judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and conſcience to change the natural condition of things, to render things eſſentially good, evil; or eſſentially evil, good; but every thing will retain its proper nature and condition, be a good or evil of the ſame quality and degree it naturally is, whatſoever mens Judgments and Perſwaſions of it are; yet mens Judgments and Conſeiences have ſuch power and influence upon themſelves, that they may render a thing good and clean in its own nature, evil and defiling in its uſe to themſelves. This the Apoſtle plainly aſſerteth, <hi>That there is nothing unclean of it ſelf</hi> [that is, no kind of meats prohibited by the Moſaical Law, to which it refers] <hi>but to him that eſteemeth any thing unclean, to him it is unclean,</hi> Rom. 14.14. the reaſon of which you have in the laſt clauſe of the laſt verſe; <hi>for whatſoever is not of Faith, is ſin;</hi> becauſe by the conſtitution of God and Nature, mens Wills and Actions are to be guided and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned by their mental Perſwaſions and Conſciences; ſo that if they counteract them, they rebel againſt their immediate Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeer and Ruler.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 9. And ſuch is the power and prevalency of mens Opinions and Perſwaſions, that they build as ſtrong a Reſolution upon them when they are erroneous and corrupt, as when they are right and ſound: for Errour is not entertain'd as Errour, but as Truth; and a man is as firmly bound by it in his own perſwaſion, as if it were Truth, and is as much prejudiced againſt the contrary Truth, as if it were a very bad Errour. Hence the Devil hath had his Martyrs as well as God; for Mr. <hi>Smith</hi> in his Remarks of the Manners and Religion of the <hi>Turks,</hi> gives us an inſtance in a <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hometan</hi> that ſuffered death rather than he would acknowledge, <hi>That there was a God:</hi> And <hi>Mahometans</hi> have been as zealous for their <hi>Mahomet,</hi> as Chriſtians for their Chriſt. Hereticks and Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks have been as zealous for their Fictions, as the Orthodox for their Faith. The falſe Prophets under the Law would as confident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly call their Dreams and Imaginations, <hi>The Word of the Lord,</hi> as the true Prophets their divine Viſions and Revelations. Hence <hi>Zedekiah</hi> the falſe Prophet ſtruck <hi>Micaiah</hi> the true Prophet, ſaying
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:105387:7"/>to him, <hi>Which way went the Spirit of the Lord from me to thee?</hi> 2 Chron. 18.23. Bloody <hi>Saul</hi> was as much concern'd for the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of the Law, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> for that of the Goſpel; <hi>I verily thought</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>that I ought to do many things against the Name of Christ,</hi> Act. 26.9. He did what he did againſt Chriſt, from clear convictions of Judgment and Conſcience; and he teſtifieth of the Jews, <hi>That they had a zeal of God,</hi> were hearty and affectionate in their Piety and Devotion, <hi>though it were not according to know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> Rom. 10.2. and ſo to no advantage. And our Saviour tells his Diſciples, <hi>That their Enemies would think they ſhould do God good ſervice to kill them,</hi> John 16.2. And accordingly <hi>Tertullian</hi> tells us, That <hi>Maximinian,</hi> who ſometimes offered humane Sacrifices, accounted the blood of Chriſtians the moſt acceptable ſort for the atonement of his angry Deities. So that men may be as confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent that they are in a right mind, when they wickedly ſeparate from the publick Worſhip of God, and the Communion of his Church, as they are who confidently perſiſt in their faithful adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 10. <hi>Secondly,</hi> Let us conſider the <hi>Conceſſion</hi> made upon this Suppoſition; <hi>Then paſs ye over into the Land of the poſſeſſion of the Lord, wherein the Lords Tabernacle dwelleth, and take poſſeſſion among us.</hi> A Propoſition full of Love, Compaſſion, and Indulgence; and a convictive Evidence, that their hearts were more inclined to Peace than War; and were rather diſpoſed to receive Satisfaction, than to inſlict Puniſhment. And in truth, whatever the Provocation be, Treating ſhould go before Fighting; for War muſt always be uſed as ſtrong Phyſick in deſperate Diſeaſes, as the laſt Remedy; and can never be juſt, but when 'tis neceſſary and unavoidable. Indeed the perſons here offended, were really the Offenders; and afterwards being better informed, juſtified the fact they now condemned, which was deſigned to prevent for ever the very thing they ſo ſeverely blamed at preſent: but they thought themſelves the wronged Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and anſwerably acted the parts of men provoked by factious and rebellious Brethren, declare the iniquity and miſchievous malignity of the Fact, and the tender reſentments they have of it; and yet rather than they will run the hazards and endure the calamities of an Inteſtine War, daſh one againſt another, and turn their Swords,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:105387:7"/>as it were, againſt their own Bowels; they ſue for Peace, offer terms of Accommodation, give the Law into their Brethrens hands, will loſe ſomething for a quiet life, buy a Peace rather than fight for it, and ſo ſuffer a ſecond wrong rather than revenge a former.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 11. I will briefly open the ſence and ſcope of the words themſelves, and then offer an Obſervation or two to your conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations. <hi>Canaan</hi> is not here called <hi>The Land of the poſſeſſion of the Lord,</hi> oppoſitely and in a way of diſcrimination from the Land of the <hi>Reubenites,</hi> &amp;c. as if that were not ſo too; but eminently, and in a way of peculiarity, from the Tabernacle of God which was there, in which was the <hi>Shecinah,</hi> the ſpecial preſence of God. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Tabernacle was called the <hi>Tabernacle of Meeting;</hi> not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the whole Congregation of <hi>Iſrael</hi> was to meet there, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was the place where God did in a moſt ſpecial manner meet with his People, <hi>Exod.</hi> 29.42. <hi>Numb.</hi> 17.4. <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.3. ſhewing by many ſpecial Evidences of Grace and Glory, that he was there, to inſtruct, protect, and bleſs them, <hi>Lev.</hi> 1.1. &amp; 9.23. and to receive Homage and Worſhip from them, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 48.1, 2. From whence by Analogy, and from the conſideration of the nature and general reaſon of the thing, we may infer, <hi>That God is in a most ſpecial man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner preſent in thoſe places which are ſet apart for his ſervice, and are appropriately his.</hi> Thoſe places which by a publick deſignation are ſet apart onely for the Offices of Religion and the uſe of holy things, have God's Name ſet upon them; and God hath ſuch a peculiar propriety in them, that he makes them the places of the ſpecial determination of his gracious preſence. <hi>I have ſanctified the Houſe which thou haſt built,</hi> 1 King. 9.3. that is, I have accepted what thou haſt dedicated; what thou haſt deſigned for my Worſhip, I have deſigned for thy Bleſſing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 12. We have the Memorials of God's Name, Symbols and Tokens to teſtifie God's Covenant with us now under the Goſpel, as they had under the Law; and why ſhould not thoſe places which are ſelected and employed to partake of them, be graced with Gods ſpecial preſence now as well as then? Place is as neceſſary for the ſolemn and publick Worſhip of God, as Time; and if ſome ſelect portion of Time be to be appropriated unto God, and more acceptable
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:105387:8"/>to him than other, why ſhould not ſelect places be ſo too? 'Tis true, the Tabernacle and Temple were places of Gods own imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate appointment, and had extraordinary Priviledges and peculiar Rites; but 'tis as true, that from the inſtinct of Nature and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Reaſon, there were publick places ſet apart and erected for Gods publick Worſhip, with Gods approbation, long before theſe places; and had Gods ſpecial preſence determined to them too, <hi>Gen.</hi> 28.16, 17, 18. <hi>Exod.</hi> 33.7. and 'tis as true, that for the ſame reaſon the Jewiſh Synagogues, which were of humane and pruden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial inſtitution and appointment, were called by the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>The Houſes of God,</hi> Pſal. 74.8. &amp; 83.10. Our Chriſtian Temples and Oratories are by him alſo called, <hi>The Churches of God,</hi> 1 Cor. 11.22. even becauſe dedicated and appropriated to his ſervice: And 'tis plain from the Apoſtles Argument drawn from <hi>the preſence of Angels</hi> with Chriſtians aſſembled in them, <hi>v.</hi> 10. that God is ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially preſent in them; the ſpecialty of Gods preſence being gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally ſpecified by the preſence of Angels, which are Gods Houſhold-Train and Retinue, <hi>Acts</hi> 7.5. comp. with <hi>Exod.</hi> 19.16. &amp; 18. <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.10, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 61.1.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 13. Hath God ſaid, <hi>That where two or three are gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed together in his Name, there am I in the midſt of them?</hi> Mat. 18.20. He hath ſaid too, <hi>That he loveth the gates of Sion more than all the dwellings of Jacob,</hi> Pſal. 87.2. <hi>for there he commandeth his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and life for evermore,</hi> Pſal. 133.3. and therefore the Pſalmiſt aſſerteth, <hi>That a day in Gods Courts</hi> [<hi>i. e.</hi> ſpent in partaking of Gods publick Ordinances with the ſolemn Aſſemblies of his people in his Houſe] <hi>is better than a thouſand,</hi> Pſal. 84.10. And elſewhere profeſſeth, that <hi>this one thing he had deſired of the Lord,</hi> as a moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirable favour, <hi>and that would he ſeek after, that he might dwell in the houſe of the Lord for ever,</hi> Pſal. 27.4. and when he was debar'd from acceſs to it, <hi>he was as a dry and thirſty land where no water is, and therefore longed to ſee Gods power and glory ſo as he had ſeen it in the ſanctuary,</hi> Pſal. 63.1, 2. which implieth, that he had obſerved that God did there manifeſt greater impreſſions and expreſſions of his power and goodneſs, than in any other place in the world. And I know no reaſon any body hath to believe that God is leſs
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:105387:8"/>propitious to publick religious Aſſemblies in his holy places now, than he was formerly. I am ſure his Ordinances are not leſs eſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacious, nor he himſelf leſs gracious, nor are holy places leſs capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious of Gods preſence and bleſſing. So that if we come hither and depart without ſpecial advantages to our Souls, 'tis becauſe we are wanting to our ſelves; we do not uſe holy Places, holy Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, and holy Aſſemblies, in that manner, and to thoſe ends and purpoſes we ſhould. And 'tis to be ſcared, that meeting in ſecret Chambers, yea, Barns and Stables, and ſuch-like places for ordinary and prophane Employments, have been and are preferr'd before our Church-Aſſemblies, becauſe very few have ſenſes exerciſed to diſcern betwixt things that differ, and know what it is to meet with God in his ways of acceptance and benediction.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 14. The next thing here conſiderable in my Text, is, That they offer them liberty to <hi>take a poſſeſſion among themſelves;</hi> that is, to ſhare with them in that Inheritance which fell to them by Lot when the Land was divided. 'Tis very likely, that a conſiderable part of the Land being yet in the poſſeſſion of the <hi>Canaanites,</hi> that part of it which they at preſent enjoyed, was little enough for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; to be ſure, they had no great ſuperſluities; and yet ſo far do they prefer Religion before Intereſt, an inconvenient Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance before a miſchievous Separation, that they freely offer to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſs themſelves, and to diſinherit their Poſterities, rather than their Brethren ſhall ſeparate from the Worſhip of God in Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with them. From whence this Obſervation naturally offers it ſelf to us, <hi>That the Church and People of God had rather depart from their Eſtates, than their Brethren ſhould wilfully and cauſeleſly depart from a publick Fellowſhip with them in the Worſhip and Service of Gods Houſe.</hi> They will rather communicate their worldly Goods to them, than be deprived of Communion with them. They are the men of this world, who have their portion in this life, who are more for <hi>Dives</hi> his good things, than for the good Fellowſhip of Gods Church. The men of God, who are expectants of an Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Kingdom, value that moſt which hath moſt of God in it, and therefore account the Communion of Saints a more eligible enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment than large poſſeſſions. The Evangelical Church having
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:105387:9"/>higher Obligations and ſtronger Motives to Love, Unity, and Peace, than the Jewiſh had, ought to be proportionably the more careful and zealous to preſerve her Communion entire and invio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late; and conſequently, wilful and cauſeleſs Separation from her, is in a due eſtimate a far greater Calamity to her, than any worldly adverſity or diſtreſs whatſoever; and ſhe cannot be duly affected with the evil of it, unleſs ſhe have greater thoughts of heart for it, than for any worldly loſs whatſoever. The Reaſons of it are theſe:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 15. <hi>First,</hi> Becauſe they are more for God than for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; would rather Gods Name ſhould be hallowed, than their own turns ſerved. If the Church of God be deſpiſed (as moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly it is, when her Members divide and ſeparate themſelves from her) the Name of God is prophaned: for the Church is called by Gods Name, and marked for his; and therefore the one cannot be deſpiſed, but the other muſt be prophaned too: and is it not better that our Eſtates ſhould be leſſen'd, than the celebrated Honour of God abated? The one is a penal evil, an evil onely contrary to their preſent well-being as men, and in ſome caſes eligible; but the other is a ſinful evil, an evil contrary to the Will, and in a ſence, to the very Being it ſelf of God, and in no caſe eligible. And you ſhall finde, when the Prophet laments the evil portion of the Church, her ſins and not her ſufferings are the principal objects of his Lamentations, becauſe the worſt evils upon her, and the procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring cauſes of all the reſt, <hi>Lam.</hi> 1.5, 8, 9. And <hi>David</hi> was more paſſionately affected and afflicted for the wickedneſs of his very E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, than for his own Exile and Reproaches, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.136. And why was it? Even becauſe he laid Gods diſhonours to his heart more than his own wrongs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 16. <hi>Secondly,</hi> Becauſe they love their Brethren as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; and therefore do not ſeek their own things as to forget the things of others, but account other mens innocencies more valuable than their own conveniencies, and conſequently more endeavour the eternal ſalvation of their Brethrens Souls, than a temporal pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion for their own Bodies. What is ſaid of <hi>Adam</hi>'s firſt ſin, may alſo be ſaid of ſinful Separation; 'tis virtually every ſin, a violation
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:105387:9"/>and breach of the whole Law. For 'tis a ſin ſo formally and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructively oppoſite to love, that if love be the fulfilling of the whole Law, as the Apoſtle tells us it is, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.10. then Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is an evacuating of the whole Law. And St. <hi>James</hi> expreſly aſſerts, that where Strife and Diviſion is, there is every evil work, <hi>Jam.</hi> 3.16. that is, ſuch men are not onely at odds among themſelves, but alſo with God and themſelves, counter-acting too often, to make and maintain a Party, their own Judgments and Conſciences: And is not Separation then a very likely way to Reformation? How light ſoever ſome men make of Diviſions and Separations, they are no other than the Smoak of the bottomleſs Pit, the exudations and workings of that fleſh which is Enmity againſt God, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.19. and the Authors of them are repreſented by the Holy Ghoſt, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding their pretences to the Spirit, as carnal, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.3, 4. ſuch as have not the Spirit, <hi>Jude, v.</hi> 19. nor are Servants to Chriſt, but Servitors to their own Bellies, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.18. Yea, ſuch is the Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of this ſin, that Divines, both Ancient and Modern, aſſert it to be the greateſt wickedneſs. Mr. <hi>Edwards,</hi> an eminent Presbyterian, and a Member of the Aſſembly of Divines, tells us in his <hi>Gangraena,</hi> ſecond part, <hi>p.</hi> 197. <hi>That Schiſm, of it ſelf, even with ſound Doctrine in every point, is a moſt grievous wickedneſs, which exceeds all other wickedneſs.</hi> And <hi>Optatus,</hi> and St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> before him, have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, That for this ſin, God more ſeverely puniſhed <hi>Corah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram</hi> (though they fell into it from a pretence to Holineſs and great Humility, <hi>Numb.</hi> 16.3.) than he did <hi>Cain</hi> for his Murther, or the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> for their Idolatry, <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 142. And Mr. <hi>Crofton,</hi> a man who preached, and wrote, and ſuffered as much for the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian Cauſe as any man in <hi>England,</hi> plainly aſſerts in the Preſace to his <hi>Saints Care for Church-Communion, That groundleſs or cauſeleſs Separation from true Churches, ſuch as he acknowledgeth and contendeth the Parochial Churches in</hi> England <hi>to be, and Self-conſtitution of new Churches, and Self-conſecration of a new Miniſtry, are fundamental Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, and inconſiſtent with a ſtate of Salvation.</hi> And he hath a very good warrant for ſo ſaying; for the Holy Ghoſt himſelf taught him, That they which addict themſelves to Diviſions, <hi>ſhall not inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit the Kingdom of God,</hi> Gal. 5.19, 20. Now if Schiſm be of ſuch a
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:105387:10"/>dangerous and damnable importance to the precious and immortal Souls of men, what price can be given too great to prevent or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem from it? Certainly, if we ought to lay down our lives for our Brethrens ſafety, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.16. we ſhould not think the expence of our Eſtates a coſt too dear for it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 17. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Becauſe there is a greater intereſt of their own, even ſelf-preſervation, requires it. The danger of a Separation is not onely to the Separatiſts, but to the whole Society of Chriſtians, from whom the Separation is made. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 9.8. <hi>One ſinner deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth much good,</hi> eſpecially a Schiſmatick; for Schiſm is to a Church, what Sedition is to a Kingdom; divides, and ſo deſtroyeth it. <hi>A Kingdom divided cannot ſtand, but is brought to deſolation,</hi> Mat. 12.25. Other ſins deſtroy the Church effectively and conſequentially, but Schiſm formally and directly: for Schiſm is to a Body Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, what a Solution of continuity is to the Body Natural; doth not like an Ulcer corrupt a part, but cuts or rends one part from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and when a compounded body is diſſolved, 'tis deſtroyed. Therefore when the Pſalmiſt aimed at the defeating of his Enemies Conſpiracy againſt him, he prayed, <hi>Deſtroy, O Lord, and divide their tongues,</hi> Pſal. 55.9. <hi>i. e.</hi> as the Languages of the <hi>Babel</hi> builders were divided, which brought their Plots to an utter confuſion, <hi>Gen.</hi> 11.7. So that Diviſion and Deſtruction go together. The Members of Chriſts Church are called <hi>Living ſtones built upon a ſpiritual houſe,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.5. Now you know, ſo long as Stones in a Wall are ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented and joyned to one another, the Wall ſtands firm, one Stone ſupports and holds faſt another, they mutually contribute preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to each other, and to the whole Wall: but if you ſever one Stone from another, 'tis no longer a Wall, but a ruinous heap. Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uniting is Church-edifying; but Church-dividing is Church-deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing work. And therefore Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> very plainly and honeſtly tells the Nonconforming Miniſters, That if <hi>they ſet themſelves in a dividing way, ſecretly to rejoyce at [the Conforming Miniſters] diſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement, and to draw as many from him as they can; they are but De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyers of the Church of God: Call your ſelves what you will,</hi> (ſaith he to them) <hi>I will call you Deſtroyers, if you are Dividers.</hi> Sacrilegious Deſertion, <hi>page</hi> 91.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:105387:10"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 18. 'Tis true, every Diviſion in a Church, and Separation from it, doth not actually end in the deſtruction of it, but yet 'tis the proper and direct tendency of every Diviſion and Separation; and the Dividers and Separaters are as really and compleatly guilty, as if they did actually accompliſh it; the ineffectualneſs of their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne proceeding from a defect of natural Power, and not of Will and moral Endeavour. And though every Diviſion do not even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually conclude in the deſtruction of a Church, yet 'tis a very heavy Oppreſſion to it, and a moſt grievous Perſecution of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 19. 'Tis a very heavy Oppreſſion to it. We are all <hi>Debtors to the Church of God,</hi> Rom. 1.14. and ſo far as we are Chriſtians, <hi>owe to it our very ſelves,</hi> Philem. <hi>v.</hi> 19. for it is <hi>the Mother of us all,</hi> Gal. 4.26. and doth not onely give us being, but alſo <hi>miniſtreth nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and increaſe to us,</hi> Col. 2.19. Eph. 4.16. and therefore we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not alienate our ſelves from its Communion and Service, without doing great injuſtice and wrong to it. Separations from a Church are very injurious to it, in five reſpects: 1. In reſpect of its Being and Exiſtence. 2. In reſpect of its Beauty and Lovelineſs. 3. In reſpect of its Fame and Reputation. 4. In reſpect of its Stability and Strength. 5. In reſpect of its Propagation and Inlargement.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 20. <hi>Firſt,</hi> Separation is an Oppreſſion to a Church, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of its Being and Exiſtence. The Church is as the Body, and we are as Members of the Body; and is it not a great wrong to the Body, for the Members caufeleſly to rend themſelves from it? If the Life be more than Meat, and the Body more than Rayment, <hi>Luke</hi> 12.23. then 'tis a greater Oppreſſion to deſtroy Life, or to diſmember the Body, than 'tis to take away outward Accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations, which are onely for Food and Rayment. By <hi>Moſes</hi> his Law, he was guilty of death that ſtole a man, <hi>Exod.</hi> 21.16. and is his guilt leſs, that robs the Church of a Saint? Man being by the very conſtitution of his nature, a ſociable creature, we cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive him related to any Society, but we muſt conceive him bound to preſerve it, and to be a Guardian to it, to protect and preſerve it in all thoſe Laws and Orders, Rights and Priviledges which are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to its Being, Security, and Welfare; and is not he an Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſor which overthrows or weakens that Society which he is bound to maintain and ſupport?</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:105387:11"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 21. <hi>Secondly,</hi> Separation is an Oppreſſion to a Church, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of its Beauty and Lovelineſs. External Beauty and Loveli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is properly nothing elſe but a reſultancy from parts harmoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly and orderly united and diſpoſed: ſo on the contrary, Defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity is a reſultancy from maimed or diſordered parts. And who is there which doth not as much dread Deformity as Poverty? What would you not give or loſe, rather than become ugly and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominable? And what are Diviſions but a diſordering of the parts of the ſame Body? And what is Separation, but a pulling of one part from another? Diſmember a Body, and you muſt certainly deform it; pluck out an Eye, or cut off the Noſe, or any other vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible part, and you will finde that you have deformed it. The Church of God, for the correſpondency of her parts in Gods deſigne and conſtitution of her, is ſo beautiful, that ſhe is altogether lovely; and is it not a great Oppreſſion to her, by Diviſions and Separations to bring Deformity upon her, and make her an Object of lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to her compaſſionate Friends, and of ſcorn to her inſulting E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 22. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Separation is a great Oppreſſion to a Church, in reſpect of her Fame and Reputation. Detraction from Fame and Reputation, is as much and more an Oppreſſion, than a detraction from any Civil Right or Poſſeſſion can be. A good Name and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port is ſuch a valuable Bleſſing, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.8. <hi>Prov.</hi> 10.7. that good men of all ſorts, in all Ages, have preferred it before either Pleaſures, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.1. or Riches, <hi>Prov.</hi> 22.1. or Life it ſelf, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.15. And the violation of it hath ever been ranked amongſt the worſt injuries in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident to humane Society and Commerce. A man, or a Society of men, without Reputation, under contempt and ſcorn, is one of the meaneſt and moſt impotent things in the world. Now Separation from a Church is an high defamation to it, and moſt directly expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth it to contempt; for this repreſents it to the world as a Society of Chriſtians apoſtatized from Chriſt, declined from the ways of God, groſs prophaners of Gods Name and Ordinances, and conſequently ſo deveſted of all goodneſs, that they are not fit for Chriſtian Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, but ought to be avoided and abandoned as Publicans and Heathens. This is the irreſiſtible inſinuation and true interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:105387:11"/>of every Separation from a Church: for no Separation, from a Church is juſtifiable, but for that reaſon which God giveth why his people ſhould come out of <hi>Babylon, That they be not partakers of her ſins, and receive not of her plagues,</hi> Rev. 18.4. So that they which ſeparate from a Church, diſgrace and brand it for a Society of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt and infamous Chriſtians, with whom God is not graciouſly preſent, and with whom good men ſhould have no fellowſhip: which is the moſt injurious dealing can be met withal in the world, and cannot be reſented without a great deal of ſmart and indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 23. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Separation is a great Oppreſſion to a Church, in reſpect of her Stability and Strength. One end why Chriſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bodied and formed his Diſciples into a Church-Society was, that from their conjunction and relation, they might, like parts of the ſame body, contribute mutual help, ſtrength, and ſuccour to each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. <hi>Two</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon</hi>) <hi>are better than one,</hi> Eccleſ. 4.9. to 13. that is, Society with Love and Peace is better than Solitarineſs, becauſe 'tis uſeful to encourage Endeavours, to ſupport under Burthens, to preſerve from Dangers, to reſcue from Diſtreſſes, to further and cheriſh in the diſcharge of Duties and Offices, and to ſympathize and refreſh under all Griefs and Sorrows. As Chriſt for his prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting and quickening influences on the Church, is compared to the <hi>Head,</hi> Col. 1.18. ſo every Chriſtian for his ſubordinate aſſiſtance and beneficialneſs to the whole Society, is compared to a <hi>Member fitly and orderly joyned to the Body,</hi> Eph. 4.15, 16. So that, <hi>As the Eye can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſay to the Hand, I have no need of thee; nor the Head to the feet, I have no need of you,</hi> 1. Cor. 12.21. ſo neither can any the moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Chriſtian ſay to the meaneſt, I have no need of thee: for they all embarque in the ſame Bottom, and are engaged by the conſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of God to a common care and concern for the whole, and one another. The Church is ſaid to be as <hi>terrible as an Army with ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,</hi> Cant. 6.1. that is, whilſt like an Army ſhe continueth in good Order, Peace, and Unity within it ſelf; becauſe in ſuch a caſe one Member is a ſuccour and defence to another: And as every Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier in an Army keeping his Rank and Order, doth partake of the benefit and advantage of the conduct, courage, and proweſs of the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:105387:12"/>whole Army; ſo every Chriſtian abiding in that Calling wherein he is called with God, walking orderly in the Church, doth partake of the uſefulneſs of all thoſe Gifts and Graces which God hath beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon the whole Church, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.22. Now we all find by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, that weak things united become ſtrong, and ſtrong things divided become weak: whence <hi>Scyllurus</hi> taught his eighty Sons by giving them a ſheaf of Arrows, which together they could not break, but one taken from another they could eaſily break, That Unity and compacted Strength was the Bond that preſerves all So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties entire and inviolate, but Diviſion that which diſſolves and extirpates them. So that he which ſeparateth himſelf from a Church, and refuſeth to ſupply his proper place and order in it, he breaks down her ſtrong holds, and weakens her, and conſequently oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth her.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 24. <hi>Fifthly,</hi> Separation from a Church is a great oppreſſion to it, in reſpect of its Propagation and Enlargement. We are all obliged to pray, and conſequently to uſe our utmoſt endeavour, that the <hi>Kingdom of God may come,</hi> Mat. 6.10. that is, that the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God adminiſtred by Jeſus Chriſt, may more and more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail, and be every where erected; or in the Apoſtles words, that <hi>the Word of God</hi> (which is the Scepter of his Kingdom) <hi>may have free paſſage and be glorified,</hi> 2 Theſſ. 3.1. <hi>by opening mens eyes, and turning them from darkneſs to light, and from the power of Satan unto God,</hi> Acts 26.18. <hi>and adding them to the Church,</hi> Acts 2.47. This is one of the great Intereſts of the Church; and whoſoever ſets himſelf to oppoſe it, is an Oppreſſor of it. You account, that he which unlawfully obſtructs anothers Trade and Commerce, and hinders him from improving and increaſing his ſtock, doth as really oppreſs him, as he that violently detains or takes his goods from him. And this is the caſe of all Separatiſts; as they do unjuſtly with-hokl from the Church what of right belongs to it, ſo they hinder it from enlarging it ſelf, by begetting Scandals, and laying Stumbling-blocks againſt its Communion and Fellowſhip. <hi>'Tis a thing both good and pleaſant, for Brethren to dwell together in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> Pſal. 133.1, 2, 3. excites Admiration in the Beholders, invites their Affections, and encourageth them to a Commerce and Communion.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:105387:12"/>But can we reaſonably expect to gain the hearts of Jews, Pagans, Mahometans, Papiſts, and Atheiſts to us, perſwade them to embrace our Religion, and to joyn themſelves to our Communion, ſo long as we have ſuch Variances, are at ſuch Diſtances from one another, and cannot agree upon terms of religious Communion among our ſelves? Do not our Diviſions and Separations ſeem to proclaim to all the world, that we underſtand not the intent and meaning of thoſe Inſtitutions &amp; Laws which Jeſus Chriſt hath impoſed upon us, and are uncertain what that Religion is which we our ſelves profeſs, and commend to others as the beſt in the world? One Sect prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth up that which another crieth down; and the religious Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of one ſort, is an abomination to another; and what one juſtifieth, another condemneth: And did you ever know diſagree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Witneſſes an effectual Proof?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 25. Beſides, will a conſidering man unite himſelf to that City which is divided againſt it ſelf? or chuſe that houſe for his place of habitation, whoſe materials are falling aſunder? and will not the Enemies of Chriſt think him an unmeet perſon to gather under his dominion and rule all the Nations in the world, who ſeems not able to govern thoſe in Unity and Peace which are already ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to him? 'Tis reported of <hi>Julian,</hi> that he thought the fomenting of Diviſions in the Church, the moſt effectual way to ſuppreſs Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, and to advance Paganiſm: and he had reaſon to think ſo; for the world will never believe that they are taught of God, who divide from one another, becauſe the Spirit of Truth is never con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to it ſelf; and the deſigne of all true Religion is to draw and binde men unto God and one another. And therefore you ſhall finde, that our Saviour prayeth again and again, that his Diſciples and followers <hi>might be one, as he and his Father are one;</hi> and to this very end, <hi>that the world might believe that God had ſent him,</hi> Joh. 17.21, 23. which implieth, that their Unity would be of principal in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence, to perſwade the world that he came into the world on Gods errand, to deſtroy the works of the Devil, and to reſtore man to Gods image, favour, and fellowſhip.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 26. And you ſhall finde, that when three thouſand were converted at one Sermon, and added to the Church, all the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:105387:13"/>were with one accord in one place, and continued with one accord in the Temple, and were of one heart and one ſoul, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.1, 41, 46. <hi>&amp;</hi> 4.32, 33. and then by the rule of contraries, they which <hi>cauſe diviſions, cauſe offences,</hi> Rom. 16.17. and prejudice the minds of men againſt the Church of God, as if it were a Synagogue of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, a Society to be ſhun'd and abhorr'd; which obſtructs the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagation and enlargement of it, and conſequently is a mighty Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion to it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 27. As Separation is an heavy Oppreſſion to, ſo 'tis a grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous Perſecution of the Church too. Perſecution in the ſtricteſt and ſevereſt ſence, is the proſecution of a perſon with a peremptory deſigne to ruine and deſtroy him. And what is Separation leſs than the execution of a deſigne to diſſolve and deſtroy that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity of Chriſtians from which the Separation is made? Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors think the perſecuted ſo bad and hateful, that they are not fit for the ſociety of men: And Separatiſts think that Church from which they ſeparate, ſo corrupt and degenerous, that 'tis not fit for the ſociety of Chriſtians. And as Perſecutors would not have the perſecuted to continue in being and exiſtence among men, ſo the Separatiſts would not have the Churches they ſeparate from, to continue in being and exiſtence among Churches. They both act from the ſame inodiating and envenomed principle, and the aim of each horribly miſchievous.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 28. Yea, I take the Separatiſts to be the worſt and moſt cruel ſort of Perſecutors: for by how much the Rights and Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of Chriſtians, as ſuch, are better and dearer to them than the Rights and Priviledges of men, as ſuch; by ſo much the more of Rigour and Severity is there in the rejection of Chriſtians from their Rights and Priviledges. Is it a very bad thing to ſuffer confiſcation of Goods, impriſonment, baniſhment, and death? 'tis much worſe to be rejected from the love and fellowſhip of God and his Church, the means of Grace, and the hope of Glory. Whatever ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderate folk may think, to be dealt withal as intolerable in the Church, is much harder uſage than to be dealt withal as intolerable in the Commonwealth; for the outward, earthly, and temporal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the Body, is onely concern'd in the one; but the inward,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:105387:13"/>ſpiritual, and eternal condition of the Soul, is concern'd in the other. When you unchurch a Society of Chriſtians, you account them, in the expreſſion of the Holy Text, <hi>as Dogs,</hi> Rev. 22.15. the baſeſt and uncleaneſt ſort of creatures, a company of men ſo far ſunk under the power of the animal life, and given over to the power and ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny of the Devil, that they are alienated from the life of God, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies to all goodneſs, to be ſhunned as the Prophaners of holy things, and the Peſts of Chriſtian Commerce. And if it be great cruelty without cauſe to be judged worthy of Death, I am ſure 'tis a greater without cauſe to be judged worthy of Hell and Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 29. And, I think, 'tis very ordinary for the Separatiſts to carry on their Separation by far worſe methods, than for the moſt part other Perſecutors do their Perſecutions; for other Perſecutors accuſe thoſe they perſecute of ſome hainous and capital Crime, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plead and try them by the known Laws of that Community to which they do belong, produce Evidences of their Allegations a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, and do not judge and execute them before tryal and conviction. But the Separatiſts from our Church, at leaſt many of them, are ſo heady and fierce againſt thoſe Chriſtian Societies from which they ſeparate, that they have no regard to ſuch mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of proceedings, but aſſume and exerciſe a power to reform, before they have, or indeed ever can, prove any thing to be amiſs; and go about to heal the Churches diſtempers by cutting her throat, and ſtabbing her to the heart, without telling her that ſhe is ſick; herein doing that to others, which they would, queſtionleſs, in no caſe have done to themſelves, nor perhaps to no particular perſon elſe in the world; as if Juſtice, Charity, and common Honeſty, were not concern'd mens behaviours towards whole Churches or Congregations of Chriſtians, as well as towards particular perſons; and that were juſtifiable towards a National, Provincial, or Paro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chial Community of men, which by the common ſence of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind hath been condemned for cruelty towards a ſingle man. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, to condemn and reject a Society of Chriſtians for the greateſt Guilts, without tryal and conviction, is one of the greateſt Outrages that humane Nature is capable of, and a thing, I am confident, the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:105387:14"/>moſt barbarous Nations abhor: And yet is not this the common practice of Separatiſts? yea, when did they otherwiſe? What Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation in <hi>England</hi> did they ever endeavour to convict and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form, before they forſook it? So that the Separatiſts have no more reaſon to glory in their Separation, than they have to glory in the vileſt Oppreſſion and moſt cruel Perſecution.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 30. And here is an Anſwer ready for them, who ask, Why we are ſo angry with them that ſeparate from us? Even becauſe they heavily oppreſs and grievouſly perſecute us, without a cauſe. They break the ſtaff of our Beauty, and the bands of our Perfectneſs, that is, violate our Unity, and quench our Charity, defame and expoſe us to Contempt, abhor us, and paſſionately purſue our Ruine; and yet confidently ask, What aileth us? and why we complain? as if they could not wrong or hurt us, unleſs contrary to the common Laws of the Land, they would not ſuffer us to live quietly in our houſes, and did beat and ſlay us where ever they met us. And yet, ſome of us can remember when ſuch forbearances were accounted great favours from ſome very neer akin to them. You may as eaſily conceive, that a man may be torn into pieces without pain and ſmart, groans and lamentations, as a Church-ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety of Chriſtians divided and broken aſunder without grief and exaſperation. When any of the Separatiſts, for affronting lawful Authority, and trampling on the known Laws of the Land, endure a confiſcation of goods, impriſonment, or baniſhment, then your Ears ſhall be filled with Sighs and Groans, with Exclamations and biting Reflections, and all the world ſhall ring of it; and yet there is nothing in theſe Sufferings but what hath relation to a temporal concern. But when they cenſure and reject us from the Kingdom of Chriſt, deal with us as intolerable, prophane, and ungodly wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, proclaim to all the world, that we are Apoſtates, and incorri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible evil doers, and as much as in them lieth, disfranchiſe us of all our ſpiritual Rights and Priviledges, which ought to be dearer to us than life it ſelf; if we take on as hurt and injured, we are peeviſh and cholerick, and have as little Reaſon to conduct us, as they judge we have of Religion. But this language of theirs becomes no mans mouth but ſuch an one as he was, who ſaid, <hi>He had rather
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:105387:14"/>have a part in</hi> Paris <hi>than in Paradiſe.</hi> They who are Chriſtians in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, prefer their God before their goods, and are more for the Communion of Saints, than for great Poſſeſſions. And this brings me to the laſt branch of my Text.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 31. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The Limitation of the Conceſſion: <hi>But rebel not againſt the Lord, nor rebel againſt us, in building you an Altar beſide the Altar of the Lord our God.</hi> The exceptive particle <hi>[But]</hi> is very emphatical, and ſeems to ſuggeſt, <hi>That no indulgence is to be ſhewed to our ſeparating Brethren, but upon condition of their penitence, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to our Communion.</hi> The Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s condeſcenſion here, was founded on a preſumption of the <hi>Reubenites</hi> Reformation. If the <hi>Reubenites,</hi> &amp;c. will yield and ſubmit themſelves to God and his Church, then they will ſtoop to them, and gratifie them; not elſe. So here, if the Separatiſts continue impenitent and obſtinate, ſet up Altar againſt Altar, and Church againſt Church, we are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der no Obligation to remit any of our Rights, or to give away any thing we juſtly poſſeſs, to them, to live in amity &amp; peace with them. We need not be at any trouble or coſt to purchaſe patterns of ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bornneſs and diſobedience, we ſhall have more than a good many thruſt upon us againſt our Wills. Church-peace is ſuch a valuable Bleſſing, that we ſhould readily purchaſe it at any rate of diſadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to our Worldly Intereſts; and we ſhould gratifie them that have ſeparated themſelves from us into oppoſite Parties to us, in any thing conſiſtent with Truth, Goodneſs, and Charity to our religious Church-communion: But if we cannot bring theſe Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders into the Church, without bringing in their Offences too, we had better give away what we have to keep them out, than to be at any coſt or trouble to make room to receive them in. If we cannot have ſome reaſonable ſecurity, that their joyning with us will do us more good than hurt, let them alone, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4.17. To ſtretch our ſelves by comprehenſive acts, to take into the boſom of the Church (as the <hi>Trojans</hi> did with the wooden horſe) a company of men armed with deſignes to undermine and betray her power, and to diſgrace and diſturb her Order, will adde to her calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties as well as to her numbers. Though they leave off their Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, yet if they retain their unpeaceable and ungovernable ſpirits
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:105387:15"/>and principles, continue more apt to finde faults in others than to amend them in themſelves, will check at every feather, raiſe quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels and diviſions from their own miſtakes and miſperſwaſions, will not be made conformable to Laws, but will have Laws made con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to them, or will live at large without the precincts of any Government at all, but what they themſelves call the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Chriſt, and will have the Wall within which we are inclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed broken and trodden down, <hi>Cant.</hi> 4.2. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 5.2. <hi>i. e.</hi> have it left indifferent how Congregations of Chriſtians and their reſpective Worſhips and Diſciplines be modelled; our Congregations may be much the greater, but our Offences and Sorrows will be never the leſs; and I think 'twill be more for our comfort and ſafety too, to go to Heaven, though without their company, in the good old way.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 32. A Ceremony or two may not be much ſtood upon, (though we are not to make matters of decencie ſo cheap, as to alter them to pleaſe every unmannerly Humouriſt) but Faith and Order, fixed Rules of Worſhip and Diſcipline, are an intereſt too conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to be neglected for any bodies ſake. All is not Gold that gli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and yet we may buy Gold too dear. 'Tis poſſible the Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratiſts may not be ſuch a good company of Chriſtians as they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves report; but ſuppoſe them to be much better than indeed they are, they which ſhall ſell the eſtabliſhed Government of the Church, and its fixed modes of Worſhip, to regain them to it, ſhall pay much too dear for it, have a very bad bargain of it, and ſhall be ſure to put all the gain in their eyes: For they are a People, for the moſt part, of ſuch volatile ſpirits, that if you have no binding Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions to fix them, you ſhall not be able to keep their company when you have it; and ſo in the iſſue the means uſed to make their company moſt ſure, will bring it to the greateſt uncertainty that can be. Take away all Order, and I am ſure there can be nothing but Confuſion: Or if it be in every mans power to be the Maſter of Order, 'tis great odds but the moſt will be the Maſters of Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rule.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 33. 'Tis therefore certainly better to keep the Church-doors cloſe ſhut, than to ſet them wide open to thoſe Separatiſts who
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:105387:15"/>would turn the doors out at windows, I mean, invert the whole or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of things, and render Religion in its Miniſtrations, like ſome late itinerant Preachers of it, an ambulatory thing, as various as the complexions of the Celebrators, and as changeable as the Moon; which will infallibly harden its Enemies againſt it, and expoſe it to their contempt and ſcorn. <hi>Hath any Nation changed their Gods?</hi> Jer. 2.11. <hi>i. e.</hi> all Nations account Innovations in matters of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Reproach to them; becauſe mens lightneſs and inconſtancy is an Argument that they have very weak heads, or very bad hearts; either that they are greatly uncertain, or exceedingly careleſs, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they pleaſe God or not by what they do. And truly, I take it to be as contrary to the revealed Will of God to aboliſh a good cuſtome, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.16. as to introduce a bad one: And 'tis very ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, that the benefit of an alteration doth compenſate the trouble of it. And we cannot but obſerve, that men given to change, are ſeldom or never ſatisfied; but the gratifying of them in one thing, encourageth them to challenge it as their due in others: Change is ſo ſweet to them, that like the Horſleaches daughters, they are ſtill crying, Give, give. And I am ſure we may be better employed than to be meddling with thoſe men who are given to change. In a word, when men, who have withdrawn and ſeparated themſelves from us into diſtinct Societies, are obſtinate, and refuſe to be refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, we muſt be ſo far from ſtudying a compliance with them, that we muſt not <hi>give place to them by ſubjection, no not for an hour,</hi> Gal. 2.5. <hi>but muſt mark and avoid them as the enemies of Chriſt,</hi> Rom. 15.16. and the words of Limitation in my Text are the reaſon of it; for they that build an Altar beſide the Altar of the Lord, rebel againſt God and againſt us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 34. The Altar is called in the Hebrew <hi>[Misbeach]</hi> a Sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catory, or a place for the Sacrifices, <hi>Gen.</hi> 22.19. <hi>Lev.</hi> 1.11. And ſuch a moſt holy place was it, both in the Tabernacle and the Temple, that it ſanctified what they offered on it, <hi>Exod.</hi> 29.37. <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.19. Now Sacrifices were Rites of addreſs to God, and uſed as Mediums of Praiſe and Prayer, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 13.12. <hi>Ezra</hi> 6.10. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.13. And accordingly you ſhall finde, that where <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> built Altars, they called on the Name of the Lord, <hi>Gen.</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:105387:16"/>12.7. comp. with 13.4. <hi>Gen.</hi> 26.25. <hi>&amp;</hi> 33.20. <hi>&amp;</hi> 35.1. <hi>i. e.</hi> they praiſed God, and prayed to him: So that an <hi>Altar was a place for ſolemn religious Worſhip.</hi> And then by building an <hi>Altar beſide the Altar of the Lord,</hi> muſt needs be deſigned, as the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> thought, the erecting an holy place for ſolemn religious Worſhip, contradiſtinct to that of the Lords own appointment, where the <hi>Reubenites, Gadites,</hi> and half Tribe of <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> had conſpired to meet in religious Aſſemblies to worſhip God in a peculiar &amp; ſeparate way, under diſtinct Officers and Orders from themſelves, who were to inhabit the Land of <hi>Canaan.</hi> And 'tis very plain, they unchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably ſuſpected an intent of ſome kind of Idolatry, and ſo took it for a deſigne of an aggravated Separation. 'Tis true, they had no ſuch bad deſigne as was ſuppoſed; yet lot the fact be ſuch as it was ſuppoſed to be, and then 'tis granted on all hands, that by ſo doing they rebelled againſt God and his Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 35. This <hi>building of an Altar beſide the Altar of the Lord,</hi> hath been applied by all ſorts of men to <hi>Schiſmatical Separations from the Chriſtian Church;</hi> that is, when any ſort of Chriſtians do voluntarily, and cauſeleſly, or raſhly forſake thoſe Chriſtian Societies with which they once had, or ought to have, Communion, and gather themſelves into ſeparate religious Societies, live combined in a ſubmiſſion to diſtinct Laws of Government and Rules of Worſhip from thoſe formerly obſerved, or were obliged unto, renouncing, refuſing, or not owning publick religious Communion with thoſe from whom they ſeparate; they are ſaid to erect Altar againſt Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, to gather Churches out of Churches, and to ſet up Churches a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Churches.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 36. Now although this be but too ordinarily practiſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us here in <hi>England.</hi> yet 'tis ſuch a very bad thing, that many of thoſe among us, who are moſt notoriouſly guilty of it, vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mently diſclaim and diſown it. That there are divers Societies of Chriſtians diſtinguiſhed from one another by the obſervation of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate ways of Church-government and Orders of Worſhip, is too evident to be denied; but who are the faulty Separatiſts, is made by ſome, matter of Queſtion and Doubt. 'Tis but to put Caſes, and the Queſtion will be anſwered; and the Doubt, if there be any, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:105387:16"/>When the <hi>Reubenites,</hi> &amp;c. built an Altar, if they had with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al actually forſaken the religious Communion of the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the Tabernacle and held ſeparate religious Meetings at their New-erected Altar, and reſolved not to be united by the ſame com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon tyes of Government and Orders of Worſhip with them; who had been the Separatiſts? queſtionleſs, the <hi>Reubenites, Gadites,</hi> and half Tribe of <hi>Manaſſeh,</hi> becauſe they onely would have departed from the Unity of the National Church, to which they did belong as Members, and to whoſe Laws of Government, and Orders of Worſhip they owed ſubjection and obedience. So here, they who have departed from the Unity of the National Church of <hi>England,</hi> are the Separatiſts: The National Church! that is a Scare crow; yea, leſs, a <hi>Chimaera</hi> dancing in a <hi>vacuum:</hi> and ſo ſome men endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to bring the old Church of <hi>England</hi> to a new nothing. They could ſwear (at leaſt the chiefeſt of them) what the Church of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> was, and Covenant to maintain her in her Doctrine, Worſhip, Diſcipline, and Government, and to endeavour a Reformation ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to her Pattern: but, good men! they cannot underſtand for their hearts what this Church of <hi>England</hi> ſhould be. One would think that a National Church in <hi>England</hi> might as eaſily be defined, as a National Church in <hi>Scotland.</hi> All the odds is, the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Church of <hi>England</hi> is not now ſo likely to ſerve their turns, as the National Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> then ſo termed, was. Let us but pull down the Biſhops, and ſet up a General Aſſembly of Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters, and 'twill be as eaſie to underſtand what the National Church of <hi>England</hi> is, as what the National Church of <hi>Scotland</hi> was.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 37. Let us reaſon the caſe a little with theſe men. Why may not the Engliſh Nation become a National Church, as well as the Jewiſh? What is there wanting which the Jews had, that is eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential to the conſtitution of a National Church? May not that be as much from God, and have as great approbation, and as many Bleſſings from him which is effected in an ordinary way, as that which is effected in an extraordinary way? What they were by immediate, we are by mediate divine Conſtitution. Were they converted from dead Idols to the living God? ſo are we. Were they united in the profeſſion of the ſame true faith? ſo are we.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:105387:17"/>Were they bound to the ſame rules and modes of Worſhip? ſo are we. What is it which makes a Church, but Gods Call to a People, and their Anſwer to his Call? Now you ſhall finde, that this is to extend to whole Nations of the Gentiles under the Goſpel, as well as it did to the whole Nation of the Jews under the Law; <hi>Iſai.</hi> 55.5. <hi>Thou ſhalt call a Nation which thou kneweſt not, and Nations which knew not thee ſhall run unto thee.</hi> Zech. 2.11. <hi>Many Nations ſhall be joyned unto the Lord in that day, and ſhall be my people.</hi> So Mich. 4.2. <hi>Many Nations ſhall come and ſay, Let us go up to the mountain of the Lord, and he will teach us his ways, and we will walk in his paths.</hi> And Pſal. 72.11, 12. <hi>All King ſhall fall down before him, all Nations ſhall ſerve him: all Nations ſhall call him bleſſed.</hi> And Chriſt tells the Jews, <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.43. <hi>That the kingdom of God</hi> [that is, the Church-ſtate] <hi>ſhall be taken from you, and given to a Nation bringing forth the fruits thereof.</hi> And 'tis no more than what <hi>Moſes</hi> foretold them, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.21. <hi>I will move them to jealouſie with thoſe that are not a people: I will provoke them to anger by a fooliſh Nation.</hi> Which the Apoſtle expreſly applieth to the rejection of the Jews, and calling of the Gentiles, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.19. which plainly evinceth, that God would convert whole Nations, as well as particular Congregations, out of them; and bring them to a Church-ſtate, ſuch for ſubſtance as the Jews enjoyed. And why may not an whole Nation incorporate into one Body Eccleſiaſtick, as well as into one Body Politick? There may be as univerſal agreement in divine matters as in civil, &amp; the Members of a National Church may be as uſeful to one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in that relation, as the Members of a Civil State, and as go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernable in the one capacity as in the other. So that they which forſake, and gather themſelves into diſtinct religious Societies from that Society of Chriſtians here in <hi>England,</hi> which are united by Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Laws Political and Eccleſiaſtical, in the profeſſion of the ſame Faith, and obſervation of the ſame rules of Worſhip and Diſcipline, are faulty Separatiſts, and ſet their Altar beſide the Altar of the Lord their God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 38. To make this yet a little plainer to you, I ſhall apply it to a Separation made from our Parochial Churches, which are of the ſame conſtitution with the National, and differ onely as parts
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:105387:17"/>from the whole. Though Parochial or Congregational Churches are no more of immediate divine Inſtitution than the Jewiſh Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation in their Synagogues were, but a meer prudential diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution of the whole into parts, for the more convenient and orderly Community in a publick confeſſion of Faith, and participation of publick Ordinances; and no Chriſtian conſidered ſimply as a Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Church Catholick, is any more bound to the Communion of one part of the Church than of another, but ought indifferently, as he hath opportunity, to joyn himſelf to any one ſound part of it as well as to another: yet our Parochial Churches being homage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neal or ſimilar parts of the National as well as Catholick Church, eſſentially conſidered, they who from Vicinity of Neighbourhood and Cohabitation, have or ought to have joyned themſelves to them as Chriſtian Aſſemblies fitly accommodated for publick Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, common Order and Edification, and beſt ſubſerving the duties of a Church-relation; if they ſeparate from our Aſſemblies, as acting in a way of Communion with the National Church, and ſet up Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies of a different and diſagreeing conſtitution, <hi>They do not walk as God hath called them,</hi> 1 Cor. 1.17. <hi>pitching every man by his own ſtandard,</hi> Numb. 2.2. <hi>according to order,</hi> 1 Cor. 14.40. <hi>Do not go forth by the footſteps of Gods flock, nor feed where God maketh his flock to reſt at noon,</hi> Cant. 1.7, 8. but ſet up an Altar beſide the Altar of the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 39. Moreover, whatever the Original Conſtitution of our Pariſh-churches was, or whatever their relation to the National Church is, or ſuppoſe there were no National Church at all, yet 'tis evident that our Pariſh-churches conſiſt of viſible Saints, ſuch as profeſs Chriſtianity, and have been baptized into the Body of Chriſt; they are the pillars and ground of Truth, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15. that is, they do preach and proclaim Gods Will as revealed in the Goſpel, which is the Word of Truth; as thoſe Pillars which have the Edicts of Princes affixed to them, proclaim their Will and Pleaſure: the true Sacraments, which are the Symbols and Seals of Gods Covenant, which is the Bond of all Amity and Commerce with God, are ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred in them; they by mutual conſent joyn themſelves toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as Paſtor and People, and aſſemble themſelves together to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:105387:18"/>of the Ordinances of Chriſt; and therefore they are moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly true Churches: and they which live in an orderly Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with them, keep the unity of the Spirit in the bond of Peace, abide where they were called with God, keep their ranks and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces where right Reaſon and Religion hath fixed them, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain publick Charity and Order; and conſequently, they which have been once joyn'd to them (as all the Separatiſts in <hi>England</hi> have been, or ought to be; for ſuch an Exiſtence as Pariſh-churches now have, they for the main had long before the oldeſt Separatiſt in <hi>England</hi> was born) to ſeparate from them, they carry it like Muti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neers in an Armie, violate all the bonds of Love, Peace, and Order, and by ſetting up diſtinct and ſeparate Societies for Worſhip and Diſcpline from them, rebel againſt God and againſt us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 40. I. Such Separatiſts rebel againſt God. As there were ſome which profeſſed they knew God, but by Works denied him, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.16. ſo ſome Separatiſts pretend to a ſingular ſubjection to the Will of God in all things, and you ſhall not lightly meet with any ſort of men who will outwardly appear more addicted to a Zeal for the ſetting up of the Kingdom of God and the Scepter of his Chriſt, as they term it, and the throwing down all oppoſite Intereſts, than they; but yet in their practices are all the while deeply engaged in rebellion againſt him. Every ſin being a tranſgreſſion of Gods Law, is virtually and by interpretation a making void of Gods Law; which is a diſclaiming his Soveraign Authoritie and Power over us, and conſequently a Rebellion againſt him: But as every breach of Law, amongſt men, is not ſtrictly and properly denominated Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion againſt the Soveraign Powers; ſo neither is every breach of Gods Law termed Rebellion againſt the Soveraign Power of God; but thoſe ſorts onely which by circumſtances are ſo aggravated, that they ſeem to be, after a ſort, a formal renunciation of our ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection unto God, a plain reſiſtance made to the Will of God, and a ſetting up the Will of man above the Will of God; and as it were a repealing of his Inſtitutions, to eſtabliſh our own Imaginations and Inventions. Now this ſin of wilful and cauſeleſs or raſh Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, is a complicated ſin, which partakes of the nature of thoſe provocations which are under the imputation of Rebellion, as I will diſcover to you in a few remarkable inſtances.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:105387:18"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 41. <hi>Firſt,</hi> Separation in the Context, is called a <hi>Turning a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from following the Lord,</hi> v. 16. &amp; 18. for when men cauſeleſly ſeparate themſelves from Gods Church, <hi>they go out,</hi> like <hi>Cain, from the preſence of the Lord,</hi> Gen. 4.16. becauſe 'tis a departure from love; and <hi>he that dwelleth not in love, dwelleth not in God, nor God in him,</hi> 1 John 4.12. Which includes an abuſe of Grace, and <hi>a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belling againſt Light,</hi> as <hi>Job</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>ch.</hi> 24.13. a ſin of knowledge and ingratitude. I pray minde it, Church-forſakers are God-forſakers; for what is the Church of God, but <hi>the houſe of God?</hi> 1 Pet. 4.17. And where doth God dwell, but in his <hi>houſe?</hi> 2 Cor. 6.16. And where doth God meet and bleſs a people, but where he <hi>records his Name?</hi> Exod. 20.24. And where doth he record his Name, but in Church-Aſſemblies, where, by the celebration of his Ordinances, preaching of his Word, <hi>Acts</hi> 5.15. performing of his Worſhip, <hi>Mal.</hi> 1.6. and exerciſing of his Diſcipline, he is known and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged as a man by his Name? And how can we obtain and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain intercourſe with God, but by coming to him, and walking with him <hi>in his Temple, and in the midſt of his golden Candleſticks?</hi> 1 Cor. 3.16. Rev. 2.1. In a word, Gods Church is his <hi>Spouſe,</hi> Cant. 4.8, 9, 10, 11, 12. and they that cleave not to God with her, <hi>go a whoring from God,</hi> Hoſ. 4.12. deal treacherouſly with God, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute themſelves to the filthy luſts of their own hearts, and do in effect ſay to God as they in the Parable, <hi>We will not have this man</hi> [that is, God] <hi>to reign over us,</hi> Luke 19.4.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 42. <hi>Secondly,</hi> Separation is a gainſaying and reſiſting lawful Authority, which is the Ordinance of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1, 2. a ſin of great pride and contempt. The formality of the ſin of <hi>Corah, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> was Schiſm, a ſinful Separation from the Church and Congregation of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> and 'tis exprefly called, a gathering themſelves together againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> and againſt <hi>Aaron,</hi> Numb. 16.3. &amp; 19. <hi>i. e.</hi> againſt the chief Magiſtrate and the chief Prieſt. They avouched all the Congregation to be equally holy with them, one as good as another; and therefore ſome were too good to be under others. And becauſe <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> took too much upon them, and uſurped a Supremacy over them, they would be a Church of themſelves, a Congregation of holy people contradiſtinct
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:105387:19"/>to them. But though they pretended for a parity, and their words ſound altogether that way, yet <hi>Moſes</hi> plainly diſcerned that their pleadings for an equality proceeded from a ſpirit ſtrongly working after a Superiority; and ſo he tells them, <hi>v.</hi> 7, 8, 9. <hi>Ye take too much upon you, ye ſons of</hi> Levi—<hi>Seemeth it but a ſmall thing to you, that the God of</hi> Iſrael <hi>hath ſeparated you from the congregation of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>to bring you neer to himſelf, to do the ſervice of the Tabernacle of the Lord, and to ſtand before the congregation to miniſter to him—and ſeek ye the Prieſthood too?</hi> They thought the High-prieſt's Garments would fit their ſhoulders as well as <hi>Aaron</hi>'s. So that their humble Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrances againſt a Superiority, was but an ambitious deſigne to exchange it, to pull down others and ſet up themſelves. And we every where ſee men like the Fir-tree in the Parable, who would be cut down as low as the meaneſt ſhrub, rather than be over-top'd by the Cedar; are ſo proud, that they cannot endure a Superiour. I will not ſay, that all the Separatiſts do ambitionate a Superiority; nor will I ſay, that like the Phariſee, they affect a ſingularity, would not be like other men, <hi>Luke</hi> 8.11. leſt they ſhould be like <hi>Saul</hi> hid in the ſtuff, men of no remark, who deſerve to be head and ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders above their Brethren in reputation and honour, themſelves be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Judges: But I ſhall be bold to ſay, they are ſo far from moving under the regular conduct of Civil and Eccleſiaſtical Authoritie, as all good Chriſtians ought to do, that the moſt viſible ſignes by which they are diſtinguiſhed from other Chriſtians, are their bold deſiances of both. And in truth, ſo far is the intereſt of the one incorporated into the other, that like <hi>Iſocrates</hi> his Twins, they live and die together, and the enemies of the one are the enemies of the other. Conformity and Loyalty, a ſtedfaſt and zealous Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with the Church, and an invincible and immovable Obedience to the King, like ſtones in an arch, do mutually ſupport and ſtreng. then one another; but Non-conformity and Malignity, Separation and Sedition, have ſuch complicated influences and united intereſts and deſigns, that the one being armed with Power, is rarely divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from the other: and he muſt wink very hard, that doth not every where ſee, that when the Church loſeth a Member, the King alſo in heart and affection loſeth a Subject; unpeaceable in the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:105387:19"/>Church, and ungovernable in the State: for they that are not held by the tyes of Religion under ſubjection and obedience to thoſe that have the rule and overſight of them in the Lord, have a very natural and eaſie ſtep to deſpiſe Dominion, and to exalt themſelves above all obligations to the civil Powers. And 'tis no wonderful ſight to ſee thoſe who from a preſumption of ſecrecie have ſneaked and creeped into an unlawful Conventicle, from a preſumption of victorie and impunitie, boldly to defie and reſiſt Authoritie in open field.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 43. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Separation proceeds from a preference of their own thoughts and devices before Gods Inſtitutions and Injunctions; which is called in the holy Text, <hi>Rebellion,</hi> Iſai. 65.2. <hi>and the making of the commandments of God of none effect,</hi> Mat. 15.6. Mark 7.13. There is nothing more plain, and more eaſie to be underſtood in all the Bible, than, <hi>That the body of Chriſt is one,</hi> and that all Chriſtians are <hi>baptized into this one body,</hi> 1 Cor. 12.12, 13. and therefore, <hi>though many, are yet one body in Chriſt, and members one of another,</hi> Rom. 12.4, 5. ſo that, <hi>if one member ſuffer, all the members ſuffer with it,</hi> 1 Cor. 12.26. From which neer relation and ſympathy, they are obliged to the deareſt <hi>love,</hi> Rom. 12.10. and are to live in the exerciſe of it, as the evidence of their neer relation to Chriſt, <hi>John</hi> 34.35. and the bond of perfectneſs among themſelves, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.14. And that this be not weaken'd or interrupted, they are commanded <hi>not to forſake the aſſembling of themſelves together,</hi> Heb. 10.25. <hi>and to give no of fence to the Church of God,</hi> 1 Cor. 10.32. <hi>nor to any member of it,</hi> Rom. 14.13. And <hi>if offences come,</hi> as through Satans ſubtilty and the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignity of fleſhly luſts they muſt needs do, <hi>Luke</hi> 17.1. (<hi>though wo to them by whom they come,</hi> Mat. 18.7.) their Chriſtian <hi>Faith, which worketh by love,</hi> Gal. 5.6. muſt ſo moderate their paſſions, that they muſt not eaſily <hi>be provoked,</hi> but <hi>bear all things</hi> that are tolerable; yea, <hi>muſt cover a multitude of ſins, and ſuffer long,</hi> 1 Cor. 13.5, 7. and ought to be ſo far from <hi>rejoycing in iniquity,</hi> and having advantages of diſlike and ſeparation, that they muſt account it their Glorie <hi>to paſs by offences,</hi> Prov. 29.11. <hi>follow after peace, and the things that make for it,</hi> Heb. 12.14. Rom. 14.10. <hi>and do as much as in them lies,</hi> do all that is poſſible to be done, <hi>to live in peace,</hi> Rom. 12.18. that is,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:105387:20"/>no condition of a peaceable Communion is to be refuſed, but ſuch as is morally impoſſible, cannot be ſubmitted unto without ſin. This is plainly the minde of God, That we muſt never forſake the Communion of that Church unto which we are united, ſo long as we can keep our innocency in it. Nothing but the ſinfulneſs of a Communion can juſtifie or warrant a Separation. When we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not continue in Communion without either the acknowledgement of ſome errour for a Truth, or the practice of ſome ſin for a Duty, we may ſeparate; but for no other provocation. The requiring of doubtful or ſuſpected practices, as ſome ſpeak, as the condition of Communion, can be no warrantable ground of Separation; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Engagements to a Separation muſt be equally certain as En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements to a Communion. They are certainly very badly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed and diſpoſed, who prefer their doubts and ſcruples before their known dutie and the Churches honour and ſafetie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 44. And I muſt tell you too, there may be real corruptions in a Church, and yet no ground for a Separation from it; becauſe we may communicate with it in Gods Ordinances, without parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king with it in its Corruptions: for that may be tolerated which is not impoſed; practiſed by ſome, which is diſowned by others, and required from none. And in all lawful things, condeſcention and yieldance is infinitely more commendable than ſelfwilledneſs, and ſtubborn frowardneſs. If therefore a Brother, much more a Mother, will have you go a mile with her, in a way of condeſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and yieldance to ſuch things as you conceive inconvenient and burthenſome, you muſt, to maintain peace and love, go with her twain, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.41. The Philoſopher calls a good man, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>a Cube or Square;</hi> implying, that a good man is not like a Spherical Figure, which is able to meet the plaineſt thing onely in a point, but like a Cubical Figure, which meets with plain things in whole broad-ſides, and hath a notable aptitude for Unity and compliance. I am ſure St. <hi>Paul</hi> was ſuch an one, and he is worthy to be a preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to us all, <hi>Who became as a Gentile to the Gentiles, that he might gain the Gentiles; and as a Jew to the Jews, that he might gain the Jews; yea, though he were a free man, yet he made himſelf a ſervant to all, and was made all things to all men, that he might gain ſome,</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:105387:20"/>1 Cor. 9.19, 20, 21, 22. And certainly, he was never baptized with the Spirit of Chriſt, who will not do more for the unitie and Peace of that Societie to which he belongs, than to pleaſe an ill-natured humour; and that will not ſmother his private judgment, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquiſh his private liberties, and his more publick conveniences too, rather than by a peremptory publication of the one, and a ſtiff main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainance of the other, diſturb the quiet of Gods Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 45. Now it being generally acknowledged by moſt of the Separatiſts, That the Church of <hi>England,</hi> at leaſt, that our Parochial Churches are true Churches, and that they may, without the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous hazard of their Salvation, communicate with them in their religious Adminiſtrations; they cannot ſeparate from them, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out exalting their own Imaginations above Gods Preſcriptions, and preferring the gratification of an Humour, before the pleaſing of God; which is a grand rebellion againſt him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 46. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Separation is an act of great ſtubbornneſs and contumacy: 'tis a ſin excuſed, juſtified, and pleaded for; which is the <hi>adding of rebellion to ſin,</hi> as <hi>Job</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>c.</hi> 34.37. The very ſame circumſtances which rendered the ſin of <hi>Saul</hi> in ſparing <hi>Agag</hi> and the beſt of the ſpoil a Rebellion, are fully applicable to the ſin of wilful and cauſeleſs Separation, and with ſome ſuperiour aggrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Did <hi>Saul</hi> break the Commandment of God? ſo do they: And far more hainouſly; for he tranſgreſſed onely a ſingle, poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, temporary, diſpenſable Precept, but they an eternal and indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſable Law of Love and Righteouſneſs: <hi>Saul</hi> tranſgreſſed to preſerve and ſave, but they to ruine and deſtroy. Did <hi>Saul,</hi> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding his diſobedience, pretend that he had performed the Commandment of the Lord? ſo do they: They do it in obedience to the Call of God, who will have them (as they ſay) come out from among us and ſeparate. Did <hi>Saul</hi> excuſe and juſtifie his ſin from the pretence of a good end and intention? ſo do they. The Church needs Reformation, and they have covenanted to reform it, and they will bring religious Miniſtrations to greater purity; ſo that they are in a faithful purſuit of <hi>The good Old Cauſe,</hi> are the men called forth to bear witneſs to the Goſpel-deſigne, and their Separation is for the Honour of God, and the Edification of his
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:105387:21"/>Church; that is, they pull down the Church to build it up, rend the Members of the Body aſunder to joyn them the more orderly together, wreck and quite mar the Ship to repair and mend it, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy to ſave. Did <hi>Saul</hi> at laſt confeſs his ſin? ſo do not they, but obſtinately defend it, yea, glory in it as an attainment of an extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary ſize; and, which is the foundation of it, aſcribe it unto God as his own doing; and are ſo far from aſſuming any ſhame or blame to themſelves for it, as ſometimes a Drunkard, a Lyar, a Swearer, and other debauch'd perſons will do, that they extol and magnifie the worthineſs of the action, and are confident that it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends them unto God, and is one of the moſt rewardable acts of Virtue they can do. This I take to be the very height of ſin, and much worſe than <hi>Saul</hi>'s Rebellion, <hi>Which was as the ſin of witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft, and his ſtubbornneſs as iniquity and idolatry,</hi> 2 Sam. 15.23.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 47. Would you not think it an abominable aggravation to the ſin of a Drunkard, a Thief, a Blaſphemer, or any ſlagitious wretch, to hear him juſtifie and plead for it as an act of Religion, and a notable piece of ſervice done for God? and hear him cenſure others as defective in duty to God and themſelves, that will not applaud and imitate him? This is the Caſe of all Separatiſts; how contrary ſoever they are to the Church and one another in their dividing and ſeparating principles and practices, motives, and ends. they impute them all to God as the Author and Encourager of them. And what higher Affront and Reproach can be done to God, who is the <hi>God of order,</hi> 1 Cor. 14.33. and <hi>the Lord of peace, that giveth peace always by all means,</hi> 2 Theſſ. 3.16. than to avouch and repreſent him the Author of Diviſions and Confuſions? There is a ſin unto death (ſaith St. <hi>John</hi> 1. <hi>ch.</hi> 5.16.) I do not ſay, that thou ſhouldeſt pray for it. I ſhall not judge any man, but ſhall leave him to ſtand or fall to his own Maſter, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.4. And indeed, what have we to do to judge thoſe that are without? 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.12. But I cannot ſee how any body can expect that God ſhould pardon that ſin which he defendeth and juſtifieth, and will not confeſs and reform, but how vile a ſin and provocation ſoever it be, will call it good, and father it upon God; and ſo blaſpheme God, rather than con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn himſelf. Now theſe particulars being duly weighed ſingly
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:105387:21"/>or together, it will appear that wilful and cauſeleſs Separation, and erecting Churches againſt Churches, is as peremptory an engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and as conſiderable a motion againſt the bent of Gods Will, and the deſigne he is managing and carrying on in the world to magnifie his Name, as any the boldeſt ſinners can adventure on.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 48. II. Separatiſts rebel againſt the Church of God too. That part of Gods Church which is continued here on Earth, is not unſitly termed <hi>Militant,</hi> becauſe 'tis always in a warfaring condition, is incompaſſed on all hands with malicious and ſpiteful adverſaries, and ſubject to the moſt invidious and miſchievous deſignes and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions. Hence ſhe is compared to <hi>a Lilly among Thorns,</hi> Cant. 2.2. becauſe ſurrounded with enemies which are as vexatious and hurtful to her, as galling and ſharp pricking Thorns to the tender Lilly. Now of all enemies, thoſe of a mans own houſe, and thoſe which have deareſt intimacie, are moſt concerned with us in civil and religious matters, are the worſt, the moſt dangerous and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitious. Here lay the accent of <hi>David</hi>'s hazards and ſorrows, That <hi>his own familiar friend in whom he truſted, which had eat of his bread, did lift up his heel againſt him,</hi> Pſal. 41.9. <hi>For it was not an enemy that reproached me</hi> (ſaith he elſewhere, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55.12, 13, 14.) <hi>then I could have born it; neither was it he that hated me that did magnifie him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf againſt me, then I would have hid my ſelf from him: But it was thou, O man, mine equal, my guide, and mine acquaintance. Tea, which was a further aggravation of it, 'twas ſuch an one as did not onely take ſweet counſel together with him, but walked unto the Houſe of God in company with him.</hi> Such a ſort of enemies as theſe are Schiſmaticks to the Church; they were born and bred in it, have been <hi>fed with her fat things full of marrow, and with her wines on the lees well reſined,</hi> Iſai. 25.6. have been taken into her boſom and made one with her, in profeſſion and outward appearance have had common intereſts, common loves and hatreds, and common hopes and fears with her, and have ſpoken unto her and quickened her, ſaying, <hi>Come ye and let us go up unto the mountain of the Lord, the houſe of the God of</hi> Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob, <hi>and he will teach us his ways, and we will walk in his paths,</hi> Iſai. 2.1. And for ſome to ariſe among our ſelves, ſpeaking perverſe things, to draw away Diſciples after them, muſt needs be a grievous hurt
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:105387:22"/>to us, <hi>Acts</hi> 20.30. becauſe all their oppoſite deſigns are managed with treachery. And doing all in the Name of Chriſt, they do as it were turn our own weapons againſt our ſelves; I mean, uſe the ſacred Scriptures and Religion it ſelf, on which the Churches Being and Unity is founded and preſerved, as Engines to divide and deſtroy us. For this reaſon, the Dividers of, and Separaters from the Church have done more to weaken and deſtroy it, than all its other Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; for Schiſmaticks are to a Church like Mutineers to an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, which by dividing it againſt it ſelf, do more certainly and ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily bring it to deſolation, than the moſt violent impreſſions from the power of any ſort of enemy whatſoever can do. Who will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard that Authority and Communion which is deſpiſed and rejected by thoſe who pretend to be the greateſt friends to it?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 49. In a word, as he which rebelleth againſt the ſupream Head of a Kingdom, rebelleth againſt the Kingdom it ſelf; ſo he that rebelleth againſt Jeſus Chriſt the ſupream Head of the Church, rebelleth againſt the Church too. Now ſinful Separation is a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remptory rebellion againſt Chriſt; for 'tis <hi>a dividing of him,</hi> 1 Cor. 1.3. and he that divides Chriſt, and makes him the Head of a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Faction, doth in effect depoſe him from his Headſhip over the Church. Hence ſuch Dividers are ſaid to be <hi>carnal, and to walk as men,</hi> 1 Cor. 3.3. <hi>i. e.</hi> walk not as perſons related to the Spiritual Kingdom of Chriſt, but as men which have cancelled all the Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations of Chriſtianity: for they cannot acknowledge Chriſt in his Supremacy, who do not keep the Unity of the Church in the Bond of Peace.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 50. Thus I have with all faithfulneſs, without partiality or prejudice to any Party, Sect, or Faction of men, repreſented to you the damnable Miſchief of Separation; and have ſaid nothing which for the ſubſtance hath not been ſaid by the moſt eminent Divines of the Presbyterian Judgment, with whom I have not a little conſulted in this caſe. And certainly, <hi>were the Scriptures conſcionably obſerved</hi> (as Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> tells us in his <hi>Chriſtian Concord,</hi> p. 119.) <hi>men would take Church-diviſion to be a greater ſin than A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultery and Theft:</hi> for 'tis an eminent branch of Antichriſtianiſm, a ſin by which men as directly and effectually do the work of the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:105387:22"/>Devil, and of the great Antichriſt his ſubordinate Inſtrument, as by any ſin they do or can commit. For 'tis moſt directly contrary to the deſigne of God the Father in ſending Chriſt into the world, which was <hi>to turn the hearts of the fathers to the children,</hi> Luke 1.17. <hi>and to gather together in one, all things in Chriſt,</hi> Eph. 1.10. And as contrary to the redeeming work of God the Son, which was <hi>to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther together in one the children of God which are ſcattered abroad,</hi> John 11.52. And as contrary to the ſanctifying Operations of the Spirit, <hi>by which we are all baptized into one body,</hi> 1 Cor. 12.12. And conſequently as contrary to all thoſe Ordinances and means of Grace by which they all derive the effluxes of their Grace, Love, and Goodneſs unto the Souls of men; which are all purpoſely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned to accompliſh the Churches unity. <hi>E. g.</hi> When we are bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, <hi>we are all baptized into one body,</hi> 1 Cor. 12.13. and what is the <hi>communion of the body and blood of Chriſt for,</hi> but to minde us, that though <hi>we are many members, yet we are all but one body?</hi> 1 Cor. 10.16, 17. And what are all the Officers of the Church and their reſpective Miniſtrations for, but <hi>to bring us to the unity of the Faith—and to ſpeak the truth in love, that we may grow up into him in all things, which is the Head, even Chriſt; from whom the whole body fitly joyned together, and compacted by that which every joynt ſupplieth—the body increaſeth to the edification of it ſelf in love,</hi> Eph. 4.13, 14, 15, 16. And Diviſions and Separations being ſo directly contrary and deſtructive to the deſigne of Chriſtianity, how unreaſonable a thing is it, for the Dividers of, and Separators from our Church, in which nothing (as ſome among themſelves acknowledge) is to be done and appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of which is unlawful, to aſſume to themſelves the denomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Godly Party? Whereas we can juſtly appeal, and call Heaven and Earth to record, that for ſo doing, they are Rebels a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God and againſt us. I ſhall conclude my Diſcourſe with a ſerious and earneſt Admonition and Charge to you, to remember with great thoughtfulneſs of heart, That the <hi>Church of Chriſt,</hi> which is <hi>the Body of Chriſt,</hi> was, is, and ever will be <hi>One;</hi> and that when you were initiated into a profeſſion of Chriſtianity, you were bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized into this <hi>one body,</hi> 1 Cor. 12.12, 13. So that here a departure from <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> is a <hi>Nullity:</hi> He that is of a New, and not of the Old
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:105387:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>Church, is of no Church. And this is the reaſon why the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Excommunication rightly executed is ſo terrible, becauſe it cuts off from Chriſt's Body; which Sentence every Schiſmatick very deſperately executes upon himſelf; and that too in the moſt effectual and tremendous manner that can be: for the Governors of the Church may, through ſome miſtake or prejudice, ſentence ſuch as ought not to be ſentenced; and then the Sentence is rever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and made void by a ſuperiour Tribunal. But whoſoever wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſeparates from the Chriſtian Church, or any ſound part of it, for a reaſon common to the whole, moſt certainly ſeparates himſelf from Chriſt too, who is the Saviour onely of his Body, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.23. The Church is compared to the Ark, becauſe out of it there is no Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation: and he that wilfully leaps out of it, is rather more than leſs deſperately guilty of Self-deſtruction, than he that is deſervedly and judicially caſt out, 'Tis a moſt fearful Curſe for a Church to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce againſt an Obſtinate Sinner, <hi>The Devil take him!</hi> and yet this Curſe every man very reſolutely executes upon himſelf, when he wilfully forſakes Gods Church: for he doth in effect ſay, <hi>I will forſake God, and the Devil take me!</hi> A thing ſo full of terrour and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoniſhment, I even tremble to ſpeak and you to hear; and from which, <hi>Good Lord deliver us, for thy Chriſts and our Jeſus his ſake.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
